Этюд — это такая позиция, в которой одной из сторон (обычно белым) предлагается выполнить задание (выиграть или сделать ничью) без указания количества ходов, необходимых для достижения этой цели. Человек, составляющий этюды, называется этюдистом.

An endgame study, or just study, is a composed position presented as a sort of puzzle, in which the aim of the solver is to find the essentially unique way for one side (usually White) to win or draw, as stipulated, against any moves the other side plays. There is no limit to the number of moves which are allowed to achieve the win; this distinguishes studies from the genre of direct win problems (e.g. "win in 2"). Such problems also differ qualitatively from the very common genre of tactical puzzles based around the middlegame, often based on an actual game, where a decisive tactic must be found.